Most harnesses, but especially Claude
Code, ship with a ton of bloat in the
system prompt. There is very likely
thousands and thousands of tokens of
stuff you're not using in your system
prompt. So, when I did mine, I found
that I had an whole stuff with workflow,
with design sync, with monitor, that I
simply wasn't using. And that is about,
you know, 8,000, 10,000 tokens per
request. Fortunately, Claude Code allows
you to customize this stuff, so you can
actually put this in your global
settings.json file, and you can disable
all sorts of useless stuff. So, I didn't
want it to control when I entered and
exited plan mode. So, I just disabled
those tools, and the tool definitions
get removed from the system prompt. I
personally really hate the ask user
question tool, so I never use it, or I
never want to see it, and so I just
removed the tool definition from Claude
system prompt. Equally, I don't want it
to schedule crons for me, so I just
deleted those as well. I don't use the
custom code review skill that ships with
it, so I disabled the bundled skills. I
disabled everything to do with dynamic
workflows. I don't use those either. I
even disabled remote control, because
there was a lot actually in the system
prompt for that. Disabled Claude AI
connectors, which were burning a ton of
tokens I didn't even realize. And I
disabled the artifacts feature. All of
that means that I dropped my initial
starting system prompt, or the system
tools, from 25K down to around 8K. I put
this in an article so that you can use a
proxy to see what you're actually
shipping, which is really, really
useful. Then, you can tune the settings
to choose just the bits of the system
prompt that you need. The less you send
over the wire, the better your outputs
are going to be, because the agent has
less stuff distracting it.